Guide to the New-York Historical Society Portrait Collection, circa 1640-2020 (bulk, 1800-1950) PR 52
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Individuals and Family Groups
  - Subseries I.E. Men of Affairs
    - Men of Affairs (copy 2; loose plates) (Box [158])
      075) Wm. Guggenheim
      076) J. Temple Gwathmey
      077) Henry H. Hall
      078) Nathaniel Haven
      079) Job E. Hedges
      080) B. A. Hegeman Jr.
      081) W. C. Heppenheimer
      082) Hugo Hirsh
      083) Isaac Hopper
      084) J. M. Horton
      085) Otto Horwitz
      086) J. E. Hulshizer
      087) H. E. Huntington
      088) Chas. M. Jacobs
      089) Adrian H. Joline
      090) E. Clarence Jones
      091) Francis W. Jones
      092) Richard W. Jones Jr.
      093) John H. Judge
      094) John C. Juhring
      095) John P. Kane
      096) John Kean
      097) James R. Keene
      098) E. J. Kehoe
      099) Bryan L. Kennelly
      100) J. Bene King
      101) H. B. Kirk
      102) Gustav H. Kissel
      103) Edward Lauterbach
      104) Chas. Lanier
      105) J. Edgar Leycraft
      106) Chas. W Mackey
      107) W. P. Maloney
      108) W. G. McAdoo
      109) Edward E. McCall
      110) John McCullogh
      111) Thos. A. McIntyre
      112) Wm. W. McLaughlin
      113) Herman A. Metz
      114) John Miles
      115) Harry B. Mingle
      116) Robt. R.Moore
      117) M. L. Morgenthau
      118) Chas. Griffith Moses
      119) Thos. M. Mulvy
      120) W. D. Munson
      121) Franklin Murphy
      122) A. Milton Napier
      123) Henry E. Nesmith
      124) Ludwig Nisson
      125) J. Van Vechten Olcott
      126) R. Morgan Olcott
      127) Geo. R. Olney
      128) R. S. O'Loughlin
      129) Richard F. Pettigrew
      130) Fred Pflomm
      131) Ira A. Place
      132) Thos. C. Platt
      133) Theodore Prince
      134) Henry S. Redmond
      135) Jordon J. Rollins
      136) John B. Rose
      137) Walter W. Ross
      138) W. J. Salomon
      139) Samuel S. Sanford
      140) Isaac N. Seligman
      141) Harry C. Senior
      142) Dr. Newton M. Shaffer
      143) Clarence J. Shearn
      144) James R. Sheffield
      145) Henry F. Shoemaker
      146) Chas. Sooy Smith
      147) Fred Southback
      148) James Speyer
      149) H. G. Squires
      150) John Stanton
      151) Louis Stern
      152) Fred C. Stevens
      153) W. L. Stow
      154) Nevada S. Stranahan
      155) Samuel Strasbourger
      156) Francis A. Stratton
      157) Dan J. Sully
      158) John W. Surburg
      159) J. Campbell Thompson
      160) Robt. W. Thompson Jr.
      161) Judson S. Todd
      162) Samuel Untermeyer
      163) W. K. Vanderbilt Jr.
      164) R. C. Veit
      165) C. C. Vermeule
      166) W. R. Ware
      167) Francis M. Weeks
      168) Chas. T. Wills
      169) James Wills
      170) Benj. Wolf
      171) Timothy L. Woodruff
      172) Joseph H. Wright
      173) Arthur G. Yates
      174) B. F. Yoakum
      175) Geo. W. Young
- Series II. Groups
  "Series II. Groups" is divided in four subseries:
  Subseries II.A.
  Groups: Small Format
  Subseries II.B.
  Groups: Medium Format
  Subseries II.C.
  Groups: Large Format
  Subseries II.D.
  Groups: Oversize Format
  - Subseries II.A. Groups: Small Format
    - Clubs and Organizations (Offsite-box G1)
      Artist's Fellowship
      Army Relief Fair, Albany, 1864
      National, general
      New York City general
      New York State general
    - Commercial Activities (Offsite-box G1)
      Groundbreaking (including Donald Trump)
      I.R.T. Company
      Laborers
      New York City, general
      New York Daily News--Party for Managing Editor Robert Shand, 1956
      New York State, general
    - Education (Offsite-box G1)
      ....P.S. 61 (610 East 12th Street, Manhattan), Miss Oliver's classroom, 1950. [Gift of Jason McDonald, PPAC.2022.018; print of scanned original, which Mr. McDonald does not have.]
    - Entertainment (Offsite-box G2)
      Poets and writers
      Sports (2 folders)
    - Health and Safety (Offsite-box G2)
      Firemen
      Medicine--nurses
      Policemen
    - Military (Offsite-box G2)
      Civil War
      ....Officers of the Confederacy
      ....Officers of the Union
      National, general (2 folders)
      Naval
      New York State
      ....22nd Regiment of Infantry and Engineers (2 folders)
    - Military (continued) (Offsite-box G3)
      New York State (continued)
      ....National Guard
      ........7th Regiment (8 folders)
      ........7th Regiment
    - Politics and Government (Offsite-box G4)
      Chinese & Japanese Ambassadors, 1860s
      Presidents of the U.S. and First Ladies
    - Religion (Offsite-box G4)
    - Other (Offsite-box G4)
  - Subseries II.B. Groups: Medium Format
    - Clubs and Organizations (Drawer Medium)
      Athletic Clubs general
      Fraternal Organizations
      ....Free & Accepted Masons, Rockland Lodge, Fellowcraft Team, 1923 [Gift of Helen Polychronos, 1999]
      ....Chinese-American: Alpha Lambda Winter Reunion Dance, 1950, and F.F. Fraternity Winter Reunion (with I.M. Pei), 1948 [Gift of Genevieve (Gene) Young, 2014]
      Historical and Literary Clubs general
      Hotel Associations
      ....Hotel Association of New York City
      ....International general
      ....NYC and national general
      Patriotic Clubs general
      ....Society of the Cincinnati
      Professional Organizations general
      ....National Academy of Design
      ....Society of Engineers
      Social Clubs
      ....Blizzard of 1888 Men (NYC)
      ....Bronx
      ....New York City
      ....Old Friends Club (NYC)
      ....Partridge Club of NY (NYC)
      ....Tavern Club (NYC)
    - Commercial Activities (Drawer Medium)
      Businesses general
      ....American Surety Company/New York Casualty Company banquet (1939) [Gift of Francine Nardone, September 2018]
      ....Columbia Mills, Inc. informal get-together, Hotel Piccadilly, December 18, 1942 [Gift of Jan DalCorso, PPAC.2022.015]
      ....Laborers general
      ....Newspaper employees general
    - Educational (Drawer Medium)
      National schools – general
      New Jersey Schools - general
      New York City Private Schools
      ....Charlier Institute
      New York City Public Schools
      ....P.S. 20, Manhattan, Forsyth Junior High School, Class of 1929, with a printed program of graduation exercises. [Gift of Judith Schiller, PPAC.2022.016]
      New York State schools – general
      Universities
      ....Columbia University
      ....New York University
      ....Princeton University
      ....Yale University
    - Entertainment (Drawer Medium)
      Artists
      Dinners
      Muscians
      Parties
    - Health and Safety (Drawer Medium)
      Fire Companies
      Medicine
      Police
      Science
    - Military (Drawer Medium)
      Dedication of monuments
      Loyal Legion
      National Guard
      ....New York State general
      ........Seventh Regiment
      ............Camp Life
      ............Celebrations
      ............Civil War
      ............General
      ............Mexican Border troubles, 1916
      ............Parades
      ............"Reminiscences of the 7th Regiment" (series of photographs taken by J. Gurney, 1872)
      ............Spanish American War
      ........165th Infantry (Old 69th New York), Company A
      ............Company photo at Camp Mills (ca. 1917/WWI); Reunion at Cunningham's (April 22, 1922)
      ........245th Coast Artillery
      Reunions
      Spanish American War
      Veterans
      ........includes 20th N.Y. Veteran Association at Gen. Warren on Little Round Top, Gettysburg, Pa., Sept. 12, 1910 (gift of Harry J. Datz, 82 S Main, Mullica Hill, NJ, 08062)
      World War I
      World War II
    - Politics and Government (Drawer Medium)
      Abolitionists
      Committee to Receive Japanese Citizens (NYC)
      Composite Portraits of Presidents of the U.S. before 1850
      Composite Portraits of Presidents of the U.S. after 1850
      International committees and organizations
      Jurors
      National government (2 folders)
      New York City government
      New York State government
      ....New York State Legislature of 1798 composite portraits
    - Religion (Drawer Medium)
      American Christian Union
      Dutch Reformed
      Episcopal
      ....includes choir of St. Agnes' Chapel, Trinity Parish, sought side of 92nd Street between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues
      General
      Methodist
    - Other (Drawer Medium)
  - Subseries II.C. Groups: Large Format
    - Clubs and Organizations (Drawer Large)
      Hotel Association of New York City
      Hotel Associations general (2 folders)
      Patriotic Clubs
      ....Sons of the Revolution, New York State
      ....79th Annual Session of the Imperial Council, Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine (Shriners), Medinah Oriental Band and Chanters, New York, July 1953 (panoramic photo). [Gift, January 2019, Evanston (Ill.) History Center] (separate folder)
      ....Schnorer Club, 1894 (separate folder)
      ....Saint Nicholas Society PAAS festival, Delmonico's, 1906 (separate folder)
      ....Canadian Society of NY, Delmonico's, 1910 (separate folder)
      ....NY Southern Society, Waldorf Astoria, 1909 (separate folder)
      ....Fraternal Order of Eagles, NY Aerie #40, Delmonico's, 1906 (separate folder)
      ....Dinner tendered F.C. wagner by Kane Lodge, Delmonico's, 1908 (separate folder)
      ....Friendly Sons of St. Patrick, Delmonico's, 1908 (separate folder)
    - Commercial Activities (Drawer Large)
      Journalists
      Lawyers
    - Education (Drawer Large)
      Harvard University
      New York University
    - Entertainment (Drawer Large)
    - Health and Safety (Drawer Large)
      Fire
    - Military (Drawer Large)
      Lafayette Post #140, New York State, Grand Army of the Republic
      ....Squadron A, New York State National Guard
      ....Seventh Regiment, New York State National Guard
      ........General
      ........Parades
      ........Veterans
      U.S. Army Base Hospital 37
    - Politics and Government (Drawer Large)
      Foreign governments
      National
      ....Composite Portraits of U.S. Presidents, 19th century
      ....Composite Portraits of U.S. Presidents, 20th century
      New York City
      ....Progress Republican Club, annual outing, 1920 (panoramic photo)
      Supreme Court Justices
    - Religion (Drawer Large)
    - Other (Drawer Large)
  - Subseries II.D. Groups: Oversize Format
    - Clubs and Organizations (Drawer Oversize)
      ....National
      Professional Organizations
      ....Lawyers
      ....N-YHS Meeting
      Other
    - Commercial Activities (Drawer Oversize)
      Newspapers
    - Entertainment (Drawer Oversize)
      Writers
    - Health and Safety (Drawer Oversize)
      Fire companies
    - Military (Drawer Oversize)
      Army of the Potomac, 1891
      7th Regiment, New York State National Guard
    - Military (Folder 2N / Unit 1A / top)
      First Annual Convention – N.Y. State Branch / American Legion / Rochester, N.Y. Oct 1919; B & W; damaged with loss; 7 x 58.75 inches.
      [In oversize enclosure with two unrelated panoramic photographs.]
    - Military (Folder 2NW / Unit 9B / Bay 27 / Drawer 9)
      • [Regimental drill hall, 1898]
      • Last review of 7th N.Y. Inft. by Brig. Gen. Philipps, Camp Wadsworth, S.C., Oct. 5th, 1917
      [In oversize enclosure with one unrelated photograph.]
    - Politics and Government (Drawer Oversize)
      New York State Electoral College
      Postmasters General
      Suffragettes
      U.S. Presidents
      U.S. Senate (2 folders)
    - Religion (Drawer Oversize)
      Methodists
    - Other (Drawer Oversize)
- Series III. Royalty
  "Series III. Royalty" is divided in three subseries:
  Subseries III.A.
  Royalty: Small Format
  Subseries III.B.
  Royalty: Large Format
  Subseries III.C.
  Royalty: Oversize Format
  - Subseries III.A. Royalty: Small Format
    This subseries is organized by country, and thereunder alphabetically by name. Royals with less than 5 images are filed in a "general" file; those with more than 5 images have their own folder.
    - Austria (Offsite-box R1)
      Franz Joseph I (1830-1916)
    - Belgium (Offsite-box R1)
    - Brazil (Offsite-box R1)
      Pedro II (1825-1891), and Teresa Christina
    - Denmark (Offsite-box R1)
    - France (Offsite-box R1)
      Louis XI (1423-1483)
      Louis XV (1710-1774)
      Louis XVI (1754-1793)
      Marie Antoinette, consort of Louis XVI
    - Germany (Offsite-box R1)
      Frederick II, King of Prussia (1712-1786) [Frederick the Great]
      Frederick III (1831-1888)
      Karl, King of Wurttemburg (1823-1891) and Olga, Queen
      William I (1797-1888) and Augusta
      William II (1859-1941) and Augusta Victoria
    - Great Britain (Offsite-box R1)
      Albert, Prince Consort of Queen Victoria
      Alexandra, Consort of Edward VII
      Anne (1665-1714)
      Charles I (1600-1649)
      Edward VII (1841-1910)
    - Great Britain (continued) (Offsite-box R2)
      Elizabeth I (1533-1603)
      Elizabeth II (b. 1926) and Phillip, Prince Consort
      George III (1738-1820)
      George V (1865-1936)
      Henry VIII (1491-1547) and wives
      James II (1633-1701)
      Mary, Queen of Scots (1542-1587)
      Victoria (1819-1901)
    - Greece (Offsite-box R2)
    - Hawaii (Offsite-box R2)
    - Holland (Offsite-box R2)
    - Italy (Offsite-box R2)
      Umberto I (1844-1900) and Margherita
    - Norway (Offsite-box R2)
      Haakon VII, and Maud
    - Portugal (Offsite-box R2)
    - Romania (Offsite-box R2)
    - Russia (Offsite-box R2)
      Aleksei Aleksandrovich [Alexis], Grand Duke of Russia (1850-1908)
      Alexander I, Emperor of Russia (1777-1825)
      Alexander II, Emperor of Russia (1818-1881)
      Alexander III, Emperor of Russia (1845-1894) and Maria, Empress
      Nicholas I, Emperor of Russia (1796-1855)
    - Serbia (Offsite-box R2)
    - Spain (Offsite-box R2)
    - Sweden (Offsite-box R2)
      Oscar II, King of Sweden (1829-1907) and Sophia, Queen
    - Thailand (Offsite-box R2)
    - Turkey (Offsite-box R2)
  - Subseries III.B. Royalty: Large Format
    This subseries includes portraits that would be considered Medium and Large sizes in other series. Every person represented in this subseries is listed by name. Countries with large amounts of royals represented are grouped together. Sitters having their own folder are so identified.
    - France (Drawer Large)
      Eugenie, Empress (1826-1920) (separate folder)
      Francis I (1494-1547)
      Marie Antoinette, Queen (1755-1793)
      Marie Louise, Empress (1791-1847)
    - Germany (Drawer Large)
      Alice, Grand Duchess of Hesse-Darmstadt (1843-1878)
      Beatrice, Princess of Battenberg (1857-1944)
      Frederick II, King of Prussia (1712-1786) (separate folder)
      Frederick III, German Emperor (1831-1888)
      Helena Augusta Victoria, Princess Christian of Schleswig-Holstein
      Luise, Queen of Prussia (1776-1810)
      Olga, Queen of Wurttemberg (1822-1892)
      William II, German Emperor (1859-1941)
      Victoria, Empress (1840-1901)
    - Great Britain (Drawer Large)
      Anne, Queen (1665-1714)
      Charles II (1630-1685)
      Charles Edward, Prince (1720-1788)
      Edward VII (1841-1910) and Queen Alexandra (1844-1925) (separate folder)
      George IV (1762-1830)
      George V (1865-1936) and Queen Mary (1867-1953 (separate folder)
      George VI (1895-1952)
      Henrietta Maria, Queen (1609-1669)
      Louise, Princess, Duchess of Argyll (1848-1939)
      Victoria, Queen (1819-1901) and group picture of children (separate folder)
      William IV (1765-1837) (separate folder)
      Windsor, Edward, Duke of (1894-1972)
    - Other royalty (Drawer Large)
      Albert I, King of the Belgians (1875-1934)
      Charles III, King of Spain (1716-1788)
      Charles XII, King of Sweden (1682-1718)
      Gorchakov, Aleksandr Mikhailovich, Prince (1798-1883)
      Juliana, Queen of the Netherlands (1909-2004)
      Juana, la Loca, Queen of Castile (1479-1555)
      Maria I, Queen of Portugal (1734-1816)
      Wilhelmina, Queen of the Netherlands (1880-1962)
  - Subseries III.C. Royalty: Oversize Format
    - Oversize royalty (Drawer Oversize)
      Albert, consort of Queen Victoria (1819-1861)
      Carlo Alberto, King of Sardinia (1798-1849)
      Victoria, Queen (1819-1901) and family
      Vittorio Emmanuel, King of Italy (1820-1878)
- Series IV. Unidentified
  "Series IV. Unidentified" is divided in three subseries:
  Subseries IV.A.
  Unidentified: Small Format
  Subseries IV.B.
  Unidentified: Large Format
  Subseries IV.C.
  Unidentified: Oversize Format [none listed]
  The cabinet cards in Subseries IV.A (small) are sorted by studio.
  - Subseries IV.A. Unidentified: Small Format
    - Cabinet cards. Misc. states, misc. studios (Offsite-box I)
      Individuals
    - Cabinet cards. California studios (Offsite-box I)
    - Cabinet cards. Connecticut studios (Offsite-box I)
    - Cabinet cards. Illinois studios (Offsite-box I)
      A-L, misc.
      M-W, misc.
    - Cabinet cards. Chicago, Ill. studios (Offsite-box I)
      Brand
      Gehrig
      Rider
      Root
      Watson
    - Cabinet cards. Massachusetts studios (Offsite-box I)
      Conly
      Douglas
      Freeman
      Hardy
      Moore
      Moulton
      Norman
      Partridge
      Rice (includes infant with technique of being held up for sitting being visible)
      Emily Stokes (photographer or subject?)
      Schillare
      Van Norman
      Warren
    - Cabinet cards. Nebraska studios (Offsite-box I)
      Rinehart
    - Cabinet cards. New Jersey studios (Offsite-box I)
      A-O, misc.
      Fitchel
      Henkel
      R-W, misc.
    - Cabinet cards. New York State studios (Offsite-box II)
      Kibbe
      Powers, A.M.
      Albany Studios, misc.: McDonald & Sterry/Sterry
      Albany Studios, misc.: Notman Photographic Co.
      Syracuse Studios, misc.
      Troy Studios, misc.
    - Cabinet cards. New York City studios (Offsite-box II)
      A-C, misc.
      Alman & Co.
      Bach, Fred
      Bloomingdale Bros.
      Bogardus
      Bostwick
      Brady
    - Cabinet cards. New York City studios (continued) (Offsite-box III)
      D-E, misc.
      Dana
      De Young
      Duryea
      F-H, misc.
      Falk
      Fredricks
      Gurney/Gurney & Son
      Howell
      Jordan
      K-N, misc.
      Klauser, Wm.
      Kurtz
      Ludovici's
      Macnabb
      Mora
    - Cabinet cards. New York City studios (continued) (Offsite-box IV)
      Moreno & Lopez
      O-R, misc.
      Pach Bros.
      Perkinson
      Pomerantz
      Robinson, A.
      Rockwood
      S-Z, misc.
      Sarony: Men
      Sarony: Women, Children, Animals
      Sarony: Oversize
    - Cabinet cards. New York City studios (continued) (Offsite-box V)
      Spamer & Spier
      Thomas, S.A.
      Wilhelm
    - Cabinet cards. Brooklyn, N.Y. studios (Offsite-box V)
      A-Z, misc.
      Pearsall
      The Windsor
    - Cabinet cards. Ohio studios (Offsite-box V)
    - Cabinet cards. Pennsylvania studios (Offsite-box V)
    - Cabinet cards. Vermont studios (Offsite-box V)
    - Cabinet cards. Washington, DC studios (Offsite-box V)
    - Cabinet cards. Wisconsin studios (Offsite-box V)
    - Cabinet cards. Foreign studios (Offsite-box VI)
      Misc. countries
      England
      France
      Italy
    - Cabinet cards. Men – In Uniform (Offsite-box VI)
    - Cabinet cards. Men and Women – Religious (Offsite-box VI)
    - Cabinet cards. Women – In Wedding Dresses (Offsite-box VI)
    - Cabinet cards. Unidentified studios (Offsite-box VI)
      Men
      Women
      Children
    - Cabinet cards. Photographs of paintings (Offsite-box VI)
    - Other formats. Men (Offsite-box VII)
      Prints (2 folders)
      Photomechanical prints (2 folders)
      In uniform – prints
      Photographs of paintings/drawings (2 folders)
      Photographs of sculptures
    - Other formats. Men (continued) (Offsite-box VIII)
      Studio portraits: Heads & half length (5 folders). Photographers include Peter A. Juley & Son, Sperry, W.H. Stalee, Kemp, Schaidner, Epler & Arnold, Bachrach, Peter M. Eotbyl, W. Stremmel,Elliott Fry, Woodbury, Bradley Studios, Steckel, Arthur Albro, Spotpix, and Pirie Mac Donald, though most of the photographers are unidentified.
      Studio portraits: Three-quarter length & full length (2 folders)
    - Other formats. Men (continued) (Offsite-box IX)
      Artists & Performers
      Academics
      Office/at desk/working
      In uniform – photographs (3 folders)
      Outdoors
      Religious – photographs
      Cyanotypes [copy prints]
      Snapshots
    - Other formats. Women (Offsite-box IX)
      Photographs of paintings/drawings
      Studio portraits: heads (3 folders)
    - Other formats. Women (continued) (Offsite-box X)
      Studio portraits: Half & three-quarter length Sol Young Studio
      Studio portraits: Same woman, four images
      Studio portraits: Studio's miniature photo sample pages
      In uniform [nurse?]
      In wedding dresses – photographs
      Indoors/at home
      Sewing/quilting/etc.
      Risque – prints & photographs
    - Other formats. Children (Offsite-box X)
    - Other formats. Children (continued) (Offsite-box XI)
      Photographs of paintings (2 folders)
      Studio portraits
      Indoors
      Outdoors (2 folders)
    - Other formats. Animals / People with Animals (Offsite-box XI)
      Cats
      Cattle
      Dogs
      Horses
      Other animals
    - Other formats. Couples and groups (Offsite-box XI)
    - Other formats. Couples and groups (continued) (Offsite-box XII)
      Businessmen
      Classes
      Recreation, misc. (boating, driving, hiking, in costume, swimming)
      Family series (2 folders)
    - Other formats. Couples and groups (continued) (Offsite-box XIII)
      Misc. series (3 folders)
      Health & Safety
      Politics & Government
      Religious
      Vietnam (man and boy, 1968; gift of Paris Teague, 2019)
  - Subseries IV.B. Unidentified: Large Format
    - Individuals. Men (Drawer Large)
      Photographs (8 folders)
      Photographs of paintings
      Prints (4 folders)
    - Individuals. Women (Drawer Large)
      Photographs (4 folders)
    - Individuals. Children (Drawer Large)
    - Individuals. Family groups (Drawer Large)
    - Groups (Drawer Large)
      Clubs and organizations
      Education
      Entertainment
      Sports
      Military (10)
      Politics and Government
      Other (3 folders)
  - Subseries IV.C. Unidentified: Oversize Format [none listed]